Shri Devi Puja. Rahuri (Hindistan) 26 Ocak 1984
Shri Devi Puja. Rahuri (Hindistan) 26 Ocak 1984
Rahuri has a special significance in the history of the Goddess,
Rahu adı verilen korkunç rahshasa bu bölgeyi yönetmeye
that when the horrible rakshasa, called Rahu,
ve tahrip etmeye başladığı zaman,
started ruling this area and devastating it.
Tanrıçanın tarihinde Rahuri’nin özel bir önemi oldu.
The whole suffered, all the God-fearing people ….
Herkes acı çekti,  Tanrıdan korkanların hepsi…
Then the Goddess took Her incarnation
Sonra Tanrıça burada enkarne oldu
here and She killed this man, this rakshasa
ve O,  bu adamı, bu rakshasayı  öldürdü.
and there are different places
Bu adamın kaçtığı farklı yerler vardı,
where how he ran, how She caught him
Tanrıça onu nasıl da yakaladı
and ultimately killed – he was killed in Rahuri.
ve sonunda öldürdü –Rahuri’de öldürüldü o.
And that’s why rahu-ri – “ri” starts from the Hrim,
İşte bu yüzden rahu-ri – “ri”,  Hrim’den başlar,
as you know that: Aim, Klim, Hrim
bildiğiniz üzere: Aim, Klim, Hrim,
are the three words denoting the three powers of the Goddess.
bunlar Tanrıçanın üç gücünü gösteren, üç kelimedir.
Aim, Hrim and Klim: Aim is the Mahakali,
Aim, Hrim ve Klim: Aim,  Mahakali’dir,
Hrim is the Mahalakshmi and Klim is the Mahasaraswati.
Hrim, Mahalakshmi ve Klim, Mahasaraswati’dir.
So, with the Hrim-power She killed this rakshasa,
Yani  Tanrıça, Hrim-gücü ile bu rakshasayı öldürdü
and then – after that killing –
ve sonra – bu öldürmeden sonra –
bhaktas started living here.
bhaktalar burada yaşamaya başladılar
And a king came all the way from Rajpur,
ve bir kral da, Rajpur’dan buraya dek, bütün bu yolu geldi,
Rajputana – and started worshipping the Goddess.
Rajputana – ve Tanrıça’ya ibadet etmeye başladı.
And went – he was a poor man, he came here as a poor man –
Ve gitti – o fakir bir adamdı, buraya fakir birisi olarak geldi –
while worshipping the Goddess
Tanrıça’ya ibadet ederken,
he raised this again into another kingdom,
o bu durumu bir diğer krallığa yükseltti
and that’s why they are called as Shalivahanas
ve işte bu yüzden onlara Shalivahana’lar denildi
because they carry the shawl of the Goddess.
çünkü onlar Tanrıça’nın şalını taşırlar.
This Shalivahanas, later on in the dynasty, was a [INDIST., SOUNDS LIKE Bhobruvaha]
Bu Shalivahana’lar, daha sonra hanedan içerisinde,
who fought with the [INDIST. SOUNDS LIKE Maharaja]
Maharaja ile savaşıp onu mağlup eden
and defeated him, who was from Ujiara [?]. Surprisingly
bir Bhobruvaha idi. Kendisi Ujiara’dandı. Şaşırtıcı şekilde
many of My relations are still in Ujiara
Benim akrabalarımın çoğu halen Ujiara’dadır
and they are following a new vision.
ve onlar yeni bir vizyonu takip ediyorlar.
So because he fought him
Yani O, Maharaja ile savaştı
many people from here shifted there
bir çok kişi buradan oraya yer değiştirdiler
and settled down in Ujiara.
ve Ujiara’da yerleştiler.
Now this Rahuri developed gradually
Rahuri, yavaş yavaş
into a very modern city,
çok modern bir şehir olarak gelişti
or you can say in a modernized.
veya modernize oldu da diyebilirsiniz
And when we go to [INDIST.SOUNDS LIKE Nankhara] you will be able to see it.
ve Nankhara’ya gittiğimiz zaman, bunu görebileceksiniz.
The forefathers
Benim atalarıma
of Mine were called as Shalivahanas
Shalivahana’lar adı verilirdi
and My mother`s place [INDIST.SOUNDS LIKE Rhaduvas] where they resided and lived.
ve onların yerleşip yaşadıkları, annemin memleketi olan Rhaduvas idi.
So Rahuri has a special significance
Bu yüzden Rahuri’nin Sahaja Yoga’nın yaşamında
in the life of Sahaja Yoga, or I should say in My own life.
özel bir önemi vardır  veya demeliyim ki, Benim kendi hayatımda da.
And that is why surprisingly that in Rahuri we have established
İşte bu yüzden şaşırtıcı şekilde bizler Rahuri’deki merkezimizi
our center in the biggest way.
en büyük şekilde kurduk.
Because the kings here worshipped
Çünkü  krallar burada
the Mother with a shawl.
Anneye bir şal ile ibadet ettiler.
Now this has a special meaning as the significance
Şimdi önemi devam ettikçe,
goes, or you can say the symbolic - it is -
bunun özel bir anlamı var veya semboliktir diyebilirsiniz
it covers the modesty of the Mother.
ve bu Annenin alçakgönüllülüğünü korur.
Mother protects us, She looks after us.
Anne bizi gözetir, O bize bakar.
So this is the one which covers Her,
Yani bu (şal) Onu koruyan şeylerden birisidir,
gives Her the grace,
Ona zerafet verir,
gives Her the protection from the cold
Onu soğuktan korur
and when the children are suffering,
ve çocuklar acı çektiklerinde
or are tired, or are sick She covers them with the shawl.
veya yorgun olduklarında veya hasta, O çocukları şal ile sarar.
So the shawl has a very big meaning
Bu yüzden şalın büyük bir anlamı vardır,
and because the used to carry the shawl of the Mother
çünkü onlar Annenin şalını her zaman
all the time in their hands,
ellerinde taşırlardı.
that’s why they are called as Shalivahanas.
işte bu yüzden  Shalivahana’lar (Şali-vahana -taşıyan) adı verildi.
So the significance of Rahuri is very great
Bu yüzden Rahuri'nin önemi çok büyüktür
and you will also see that
ve bunu siz de göreceksiniz,
in the gross also the people here are very receptive to Sahaja Yoga.
insanlar büyük ölçüde Sahaja Yoga’ya karşı açıklar.
Even the factory people – I went to see them before I came here,
Fabrikadaki insanlar bile- buraya gelmeden önce Ben onları görmeye,
to talk to them. And they are so much submerged
onlarla konuşmaya gittim. Sahaya Yoga’daki gelişmelere
in the developments of Sahaja Yoga
o kadar çok daldılar ki,
and amount of things they want to do,
yapmak istedikleri şeyin miktarı
and want to take advantage of Sahaja Yoga here.
ve burada Sahaja Yoganın avantajlarını almak istemeleri.
As they are built for you especially too
Özellikle onlar bunu sizin için inşa ettiler,
was made with great care about from that they thought
biteceğini düşünerek büyük bir
that it was finished and worked very hard.
özenle yaptılar ve çok çalıştılar.
Day and night, just to prepare this hall for you.
Sadece bu salonu sizlere hazırlamak için, gece gündüz çalıştılar.
So this is how it is going to work out,
İşte bu, bu şekilde çalışacaktır
and last time I told them that you should not make
ve son seferinde Ben onlara, bu şeker kamışlarından
an alcohol out of these molasses
alkol üretmemelisiniz dedim.
[??] and sell it at the market at a cheap rate,
Pazarda ucuz bir fiyata satın,
but make something useful.
ama yararlı bir şeyler yapın.
So they are trying to find out
Bu nedenle şimdi,  onlarla konuştuğum
a technique about which I talked to them now.
bir tekniği bulmaya çalışıyorlar.
So they are very religious people also.
Yani çok dindar insanlar onlar aynı zamanda.
by removing all these addictions among the people.
bir çok insanı düzeltmeye çalşıyorlar.
So that is the significance of Rahuri-Puja
Yani, Rahuri Pujanın önemi budur
and that’s what it is, that you are like Shalivahanas
ve bu, onun olduğu şeydir. Sizler Anneye ve Onun şalına
who are worshipping the Mother and Her shawl.
ibadet eden Shalivahana’lar gibisiniz.
So today’s Puja has a special significance
Bu yüzden bu günkü pujanın özel bir önemi var,
– that’s why Rahuri we have very good Sahaja Yogis here,
işte bu yüzden burada, Rahuri’de çok iyi, çok ilerlemiş,
very developed, very evolved, moral people.
çok gelişmiş Sahaja Yogilerimiz var, ahlaklı insanlar.
They are not scholars of Sanskrit,
Sankritçenin alimleri değiller
but they are scholars of Sahaja Yoga.
ama Sahaja Yoganın alimleri onlar.
There is a difference between being a scholar of Sanskrit
Sankritçenin alimi olmakla, Sahaja Yoganın alimi
and a scholar of Sahaja Yoga.
olmak arasında bir fark var.
Now for you people I hope it has been a comfortable
Şimdi umarım,  burada sizlerin rahat bir konaklamanız oldu
stay for you here and
ve umarız ki gelecekte de,
we hope also for the future you are going to enjoy
seyahatinizden neşe duyacaksınız
your journey and enjoy the bliss of the Divine!
ve Tanrının mutluluğundan neşe duyarsınız.
[Shri Mataji talks in Marathi]
[Shri Mataji, Marathi dilinde konuşuyor]
We don’t read about Rahul`s killing,
Bizler Rahul’un öldürülüşünü okumadık
because it is Mahalakshmi who killed,
çünkü onu öldüren Mahalakshmi’dir
but what we read in the Devi-Mahatmya is the Mahakali`s powers.
ama Devi-Mahatmya’da okuduğumuz şey, Mahakali`nin güçleridir.
But Rahul was killed here in Rahuri by Mahalakshmi,
Ama Rahul, Mahalakshmi tarafından burada Rahuri’de öldürüldü
and that Mahalakshmi power is called as Hrim power,
ve bu Mahalakshmi gününe, Hrim gücü adı verilir,
so that’s why this is Rahu-ri.
işte bu yüzden bu,  Rahu-ri’dir.
Actually it is Rahu-hrim we can say it is Rahu-ri to make it simple.
Gerçekte bu Rahu-hrim bunu basitleştirmek için Rahu-ri  diyebiliriz.
[Shri Mataji talks in Marathi]
[Shri Mataji, in Marathi dilinde konuşuyor]
And according to that calendar only
Ve tüm Maharashtralılar sadece
all the Maharashtrians are living,
bu takvime göre yaşıyorlar.
which is very, I should say, much more subtler than vikram,
Bu çok, söylemeliyim ki, vikram’dan, bu şeyden çok daha süptil.
this thing. Because in the [INDIST.SOUNDS LIKE: vikram-panjaga]
Çünkü vikram-panjaga’da, bu yere
this area is still called as Kali-Yuga, Kali-Yuga,
hala Kali Yuga adı verilir, Kali Yuga.
but in this [INDIST: SOUNDS LIKE: panjaga; Then: Shalivahana-Panjaga]
Ama bu panjaga; sonra: Shalivahana-Panjaga,
it is called as Krita-Yuga. It’s much subtler.
Krita-Yuga olarak adlandırıldı.
That’s a very wider thing
Bu çok daha süptildir. Bu çok daha geniş bir şey
and it doesn’t give you the different sections
ve size Kali Yuganın farklı kısımlarını vermiyor,
of Kali-Yuga, that how it becomes Krita-Yuga
işte Krita Yuga böyle başladı
The calendar that was used by the North Indians
Kuzey Hindistanlılar tarafından kullanılan takvim Vikram’dı
was the Vikram, and the South Indians used the Shalivahana,
ve Güney Hindistanlılar için ise Shalivahana idi,
but especially in Maharashtra. But the support came mainly from
ama özellikle de Maharashtra’da. Destek,  ağırlıklı olarak
[INDIST.] direct, who said that this is the better [INDIST.SOUNDS LIKE: panjaga]
doğrudan doğruya bunun daha iyi olduğunu söyleyen panjaga’dan geldi
because it deals with subtler side of time.
çünkü o,  zamanın süptil tarafı ile ilgilenir.
Subtler side of time.
Zamanın daha süptil olan tarafı.
And that’s why it was regarded as a greater thing.
İşte bu yüzden de bu, daha büyük bir şey olarak adledildi.
Now on the first day of
Şimdi, bu takvimin ilk gününde,
this calendar they put a kalasha
bir bayrak asar gibi,
[? A pot] with a shawl as a banner, a kalasha and a shawl as a banner.
üzerinde bir bir şal olan bir kalasha (çömlek) koyarlar, bayrak gibi
That’s why kalash, which is the Kundalini, is the Aquarius.
bir şal ve bir kalasha. İşte kalash, kundalinidir, Kova burcu.
[Shri Mataji talks in Marathi]
[Shri Mataji, Marathi dilinde konuşuyor]
In the older days all the Maharashtrian women used to have
Eski günlerde, Maharashtralı kadınlar bir tür
some sort of an additional cloth, a shawl, which they used to carry.
ilave giysi kullanırlardı, taşıdıkları bir şal vardı.
If it was a marriage then they used to have a marriage sari,
Eğer bu bir evlilik ise, o zaman bir şal ile tamamlanan
[INDIST.SOUNDS LIKE: completed with that shawl].
evlilik sarisi kullanırlardı.
All the time they had to wear something, a covering over the sari.
Her zaman üstüne bir şey giymeleri gerekirdi, sariyi örten bir şey.
Sari was not the end-cloth but now we have become modern,
En üste giyilen sari değildi ama şimdi biz modernleştik, buyüzden de
so we don’t use the, that, another cloth which one has to use.
bunu kullanmıyoruz, kişinin kullanmaması gereken, başka bir kıyafet.
So, but this is only the custom.
Bu yüzden bu sadece bir gelenek.
In India is not the point, it is not only in Maharashtra, everywhere.
Hindistan’da mesele bu değil sadece Maharashtra’da değil, heryerde
But there, because a dress was not a sari,
ama orada, çünkü oralarda sari değil de bir elbise giyilir
but those who bore the sari did not use, in the North.
ama sariden sıkılanlar kullanmazlar, kuzeyde.
But here those who use the sari also use the shawl, on top of that.
Ama burada sari kullananlar aynı zamanda üzerinde şalda kullanırlar.
And that’s why, you see, this country has a speciality,
İşte bu yüzden, bakın, bu ülkenin bir özelliği var,
this part that they always had this shawl,
bu bölgede onların her zaman şalları oldu,
whether they went out, for their protection,
dışarı çıksalarda kendi korunmaları için
or they went for a marriage
veya bir düğüne veya bir yere gittiklerinde,
or anything they used to have another thing on top.
bunun üzerinde başka bir şey kullanırlardı.
Now of course we have, symbolically, something modernized.
Şimdi, tabii ki sembolik olarak modernize olmuş bir şeyler sahibiz.
This is, wearing little pieces to be used as shawls.
Bugün, şal olarak küçük parçalar kullanılmakta.
You see, everything is getting modernized.
Bakın, her şey modernleşiyor.
[Shri Mataji talks in Marathi]
[Shri Mataji, Marathi dilinde konuşuyor]
You must, all right, touch the feet of this Rahuri-Land.
Sizler, tamam, Rahuri- diyarının ayaklarına dokunmak zorundasınız.
Then after, Ganesha, we must also touch the feet.
Ondan sonra, Ganesha, onun da ayağına dokunmak zorundayız.
As soon as I get the land, first we establish Ganesha here,
Ben bu yeri alır almaz, Ganesha’yı burada yerleştirdik
and once this land, we get
ve bu yer bir kez, bütün dünyada,
everywhere in the whole world, we get land
her yerde yerler aldık, toprak aldık
and we have no problems of any kind as far as the land is concerned.
ve yer sözkonusu olunca hiç bir problemimiz yok.
When the Ashram is built here, everywhere in the whole world
Ashram burada inşa edildiği zaman, bütün dünyada, her yerde,
we’ll have Ashrams. So the beginning has to be at the right place.
ashramlarımız olacak. Bu yüzden başlangıç doğru yerden olmalıdır.
[Shri Mataji talks in Marathi]
[Shri Mataji, Marathi dilinde konuşuyor]
They have come all the way from Germany.
Onlar ta Almanya’dan buraya bütün yolu geldiler.
[Shri Mataji talks in Marathi; then the Puja starts]
[Shri Mataji, Marathi dilinde konuşuyor, sonra da puja başlıyor]
[during the Puja:] Husband and wife, are you? Ha?
Siz karı koca mısınız? Ha?
You both are husband and wife – are you?
İkiniz karı ve kocasınız – değil mi?
You have to be husband and wife! [Yogi: Yes!]
Karı ve koca olmalısınız! Yogi: Evet!
Shri Mataji: You are? You both are husband and wife? [Yogi: Not!]
Siz? İkiniz karı ve koca mısınız? Yogi: Değiliz!
Shri Mataji: Yes! [Shri Mataji talks in Marathi]
[Shri Mataji, Marathi dilinde konuşuyor]
Means: the husband and wife should sit together!
Bunun anlamı şu: Karı ve koca beraber oturmalıdır!
That’s the only time when a man and a woman
Bu bir kadın ve adamın bu ülkede
sits together in this country. Not the brother.
beraber oturabileceği tek zamandır.
Not even sisters and brothers. Only husband and wife.
Erkek kardeşle değil, kız kardeşle bile değil. Sadece karı ve koca.